# 河南黄焖羊肉
Henan Huang Men Yang Rou (Braised fried lamb)
# 俺过年时候经常吃的一道菜
A dish that I usually have during Chinese New Year
# 香啊
Tastes so good
# 今天我带过来的是羊腿肉 前腿
The meat that I brought here is the front leg of a lamb
# 这样的油给它剔掉
Remove the fat like this
# 给它切成小的滚刀块
Cut into small dices
# 有时候切太大了它不好蒸
It's hard to steam if cut too large
# 蒸时间比较长
The steaming will take a while
# 过春节啊 结婚宴啊 大席桌
During spring festival, or on weddings and large banquets
# 这个菜是离不开的
You will always see this dish
# 好 腌制一下
Ok. Marinate it for a while
# 干辣椒 两截儿
Dried chili. Two sections
# 微微的辣味
Slight spicy
# 花椒 七八个
Sichuan peppercorns. 7 or 8
# 羊肉还是喜欢花椒的
Lamb matches well with Sichuan peppercorns
# 放个大料 姜片 两个马蹄葱
Add some star anise, ginger slices, and two pieces of green onion
# 倒一点点黄酒
Just a little bit huangjiu rice wine
# 盐 这个里边别太咸了
Salt. Don't make it too salty
# 因为汤里面还带一点点味道
because the soup would be a bit salty as well
# 老家的一个感觉
A tradition in my hometown
# 就是一定要放一点点十三香
is to add some 'thirteen-spices'
# 我们豫中平原这一块
In the middle Henan plains
# 基本上吃什么都有
You may see all types of food
# 五香粉 十三香离不开
but all of them come with five-spices or thirteen-spices
# 白糖来一点点 就是提鲜的
A bit of sugar to elevate the umami taste
# 入一下味 腌一会
Let the flavor penetrate. Marinate it for a while
# 咱们这时候打个糊
Let's make a batter now
# 蒸酥肉
Steamed deep-fried meat
# 这道菜实惠啊
That's a fulfilling dish
# 打这糊呢 不需要脆皮糊
This batter is not a crispy batter
# 也不需要软炸糊
not a soft-fry batter either
# 也不能太酥了 因为它是蒸么
You shouldn't make it too crispy. We need to steam it after all
# 只是放一点面粉
Just some flour
# 这个面粉跟淀粉的比例
The ratio between flour and starch
# 就是二比一
is 2:1
# 面粉一定是二 淀粉是一
Two portions of flour, one portion of starch
# 搁一鸡蛋这糊一蒸就软和了
Add an egg and the batter will be soft after steaming
# 加一点点水
A little water
# 打这个糊的时候不能太稠了
The batter shouldn't be too heavy
# 你看它稍微一拉能拉出线来
See? Lift it and it'll give a stream
# 拉出一条线
A stream
# 这时候羊肉也正好行了
Now the lamb is ready
# 咱们把这糊给倒在羊肉里面
Let's pour the batter into the lamb
# 正合适
Right amount
# 又不过分的稠 也不稀
Not too heavy, but not light
# 充分的抓在上面了
The batter perfectly wraps the lamb
# 这时候咱们油也烧好了
Now the oil temperature is high enough
# 油温在四成到五成热就行
The temperature should be between 120 and 150 degrees celsius
# 这就合适 这还到不了五成呢
That's right. Not 150 degrees yet
# 还有一个给咱网友说一声
One more thing to be careful about
# 炸东西的时候
When frying stuff
# 一定要离油近一点
Make sure you put it close enough to the oil surface
# 越近它越不崩 挨着油下
The closer it is, the less oil will be splashed
# 他越害怕越烫手
You'll definitely burn yourself if you are afraid
# 你看刚才在腌制的
Look. The ginger and green onion that we use for marinating
# 葱跟姜直接就炸里边
will also be put into the oil
# 它一炸稍微的一起就行了
As soon as the batter slightly swells up, it's done
# 一定要给它稍微炸干一点点
Make sure you fry it until it's dry
# 等一下咱们蒸的时候它会吸
The meat will absorb the...
# 完全吸收原汤
original broth when steaming
# 然后蒸出来更加酥烂
And it'll be more soft after steaming
# 咱们这就是一次炸成 一次炸好
We just need to fry it once
# 然后这时候咱们看这个糊
And the batter...
# 完全给它炸的就是
As you can hear
# 一听哗啦哗啦响
the noise from colliding batter
# 而且咱们这个肉基本上也炸熟了
Also the meat is almost cooked now
# 这时候咱们就可以关火
Let's turn off the heat now
# 好 下一步调汤
Ok. Let's make a sauce
# 放点底油
Some base oil
# 一点点花椒粒
Some Sichuan peppercorns
# 葱姜
Green onion and ginger
# 然后放一点点酱油
Some soysauce
# 加点水
Some water
# 这个颜色你看 说红不红
The color is a bit red
# 而且也不能太红 也不能太黑了
It shouldn't be too red, nor too dark
# 有时候煮个羊肉
If you want to make a lamb soup
# 煮个汤 加里面味道更好
You can also add this sauce to the soup
# 这时候咱们稍微调一下
Let's season it
# 因为刚才已经加盐了
We just added some salt
# 我们这时候也放一点点盐
So we add a bit more salt here
# 放一点点十三香
and a bit 'thirteen-spices'
# 来一点点白胡椒粉
Some white pepper powder
# 白胡椒粉
white pepper powder
# 好了 其实特别简单
Done. This is actually a very simple dish
# 这时候咱们把这个汤灌上
Pour the sauce into the meat
# 这时候咱们放个大料
Add a star anise
# 放点葱放点姜
Some ginger and green onion
# 上笼屉 蒸一个小时
Put into the steam pot and steam for one hour
# 来碗蒸羊肉
Let's have steamed lamb
# 一个小时到了
That's one hour
# 拿筷子把这料头拣出来
Pick out the ingredients with chopsticks
# 大料 河南八大碗之一
-Star anise. - One of the 'Eight Special Bowls' in Henan
# 在我们家里边
In my home
# 你也可以倒出来
You can pour the lamb into a larger plate
# 也可以不倒出来
Or not
# 也可以在碗里边
Just keep it in the bowl
# 香油就是一点点
A little bit seasame oil
# 河南黄焖羊肉 忒好咧
Henan Huang Men Yang Rou (Braised fried lamb). Fantastic
# 怎么样啊
How is it?
# 香啊
Tastes so good
# 还是有点意思
That's interesting
# 里边很筋道 还有嚼头
It's chewy inside
# 李党出锅点了几滴香油
Li Dang added a few drops of seasame oil before serving
# 这个太妙了
This is a great trick
# 这一下这味儿 就激发出来了
The flavor is activated immediately
# 用酥肉这种方式做羊肉
Cooking lamb by deep-frying
# 咱们在北京地区还不常见
Is a pretty rare method in Beijing
# 出来效果也非常好吃
It is very delicious indeed
# 高手在民间
Masters always hide in the public
# 二伯这一句话就总结性发言
That's a great summary, Er Bai